<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<MetaDocs>
  <DocumentationNarrativeList>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:cli:narrative:summary:cli" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:cli">
      <Body>Command-line tools for BI modeling, conversion, validation, and execution.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>PlainText</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>CLI</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:models:narrative:summary:models" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:models">
      <Body>Model references for the sanctioned BI metadata workspaces.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>PlainText</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>Models</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:summary:overview" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:overview">
      <Body>`meta-bi` is a model-driven BI engineering stack built on the generic `meta` foundation. It keeps source structures, SQL semantics, transformation contracts, data architecture, deployment assets, execution plans, and analytical targets as typed workspaces that can be inspected, converted, generated, and executed through one model-first foundation.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>Overview</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:cli:narrative:summary:cli" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:cli">
      <Body>Command-line tools for the core metadata foundation.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>PlainText</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>CLI</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:models:narrative:summary:models" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:models">
      <Body>Model references for the core metadata foundation.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>PlainText</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>Models</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:cliataglance:meta-cli-at-a-glance" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:workspacecontract:workspace-contract">
      <Body>`meta` follows the working lifecycle of a metadata workspace:

- **Create and inspect:** initialize workspaces and inspect their current model and instance state (`init`, `status`).
- **Explore:** list, view, query, and traverse modeled data (`list`, `view`, `query`, `graph`).
- **Author:** change model definitions and instance data through model-aware commands (`model ...`, `insert`, `delete`, `bulk-insert`, `instance ...`).
- **Refactor:** analyze candidate relationships and apply atomic model-plus-instance changes (`model suggest`, `model refactor ...`).
- **Exchange representations:** import source material and generate SQL, C#, and other sanctioned consumables (`import ...`, `generate ...`).

A typical flow starts with a model and instance workspace, uses `meta` to preserve and transform that modeled truth, then emits the native artifacts needed by databases, applications, and downstream generators.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>CliAtAGlance</Slot>
      <Title>Meta CLI at a glance</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:commandguide:command-guide" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:installandrun:install-and-run">
      <Body>Workspace-oriented commands use the **current working directory** when `--workspace` is omitted. They do not search parent directories. Use `--workspace &lt;path&gt;` when the target workspace is elsewhere.

Common command behavior:

- successful state changes print `Ok`;
- usage and runtime failures explain what prevented the command from continuing and return a non-zero exit code;
- mutating commands that expose `--strict` promote warnings to errors.

**Discover the command surface**

```powershell
meta help
meta help model
meta model suggest --help
```

Top-level help lists command groups. Command help then narrows the surface to the relevant usage, arguments, and options.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>CommandGuide</Slot>
      <Title>Command guide</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:foundations:metadata-foundations" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:repositoryclis:repository-clis">
      <Body>In this project, metadata is not an annotation around the product. **Metadata is the product model itself.**

- **`model.xml`** declares the schema contract: entities, scalar properties, and relationships.
- **`instances/*.xml`** carries the instance graph for that model: records, values, and relationship usages.
- **`workspace.xml`** records workspace-level representation and storage configuration.

Core terms:

- **Model:** a named set of entity definitions.
- **Entity:** a record type, comparable to a table or a POCO type.
- **Property:** a scalar attribute on an entity instance.
- **Relationship:** a modeled reference from one entity to another.
- **Instance:** one identified record of an entity.
- **Workspace:** an on-disk unit containing a model, its instances, and workspace configuration.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Foundations</Slot>
      <Title>Metadata foundations</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:installandrun:install-and-run" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:instancexmlcontract:instance-xml-contract">
      <Body>Build the foundation and weave solutions with .NET 8:

```powershell
dotnet build Metadata.Framework.sln
dotnet build MetaWeave.sln
```

Run a CLI directly from its project during development:

```powershell
dotnet run --project Meta/Cli/Meta.Cli.csproj -- help
```

When the CLI output directory is on `PATH`, use the executable name directly:

```powershell
meta help
```

On Windows, the `meta`, `meta-weave`, and `meta-docs` project builds also refresh their framework-dependent publish directories under `Cli\bin\publish\win-x64`.

Build the offline installer package with:

```powershell
powershell -NoProfile -ExecutionPolicy Bypass -File Meta\Installer\package-offline.ps1
```

The default package is framework-dependent and requires the .NET 8 runtime on the target machine. Use `-SelfContained` only when the package must carry its own runtime.

Install the packaged `meta`, `meta-weave`, and `meta-docs` CLIs into `%LOCALAPPDATA%\meta\bin` with:

```powershell
Meta\Installer\bin\publish\win-x64-framework-dependent-shared\install-meta.exe
```</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>InstallAndRun</Slot>
      <Title>Install and run</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:instancexmlcontract:instance-xml-contract" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:modelxmlcontract:model-xml-contract">
      <Body>`instances/*.xml` carries the data for a model.

- The document root is the model name, such as `&lt;EnterpriseBIPlatform&gt;`.
- Each entity's records appear under a deterministic list container such as `&lt;CubeList&gt;` or `&lt;MeasureList&gt;`.
- Each record uses the singular entity name and has an `Id="..."` attribute.
- Relationship usages are stored as `...Id` attributes. A relationship to `Cube` becomes `CubeId`; a relationship with `role="SourceCube"` becomes `SourceCubeId`.
- Scalar properties are child elements. A missing element is unset; an empty element is an explicitly empty string.

These XML conventions are deterministic representation rules. The loaded C# model still carries relationships as object references, while generated SQL carries them as relational keys.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>InstanceXmlContract</Slot>
      <Title>Instance XML contract</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:internalpackages:internal-packages" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:commandguide:command-guide">
      <Body>The foundation libraries are available as internal NuGet packages:

- `Meta.Core`
- `Meta.Adapters`
- `MetaWeave.Core`

Build them into the local `.nupkg` feed with:

```powershell
.\pack-internal.cmd
```

Downstream repositories consume packages rather than project references back into this repository. That keeps the foundation boundary explicit and prevents downstream changes from silently reaching into core source.

`meta-bi` currently consumes `Meta.Core` from this feed. `MetaWeave.Core` is published alongside it for consumers that need sanctioned cross-model binding services.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>InternalPackages</Slot>
      <Title>Internal packages</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:isomorphism:why-isomorphic-metadata" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:foundations:metadata-foundations">
      <Body>Isomorphic metadata preserves the **same structure and meaning** across its supported representations instead of translating each representation into a different product model.

One model can therefore have three native working surfaces, each suited to a different kind of work:

- **XML workspace:** deterministic, reviewable, and git-friendly for authoring and version control.
- **SQL:** relational and database-native, with keys and constraints carrying integrity where data platforms already work.
- **C#:** application-native, with strongly typed objects and object references for tools, services, and generated consumers.

Because the semantics remain aligned, different producers and consumers can collaborate without rebuilding the model at every boundary:

- analysts and modelers can author and review workspace data;
- platform engineers can consume SQL and SQL-project outputs;
- application and tooling engineers can consume generated C# APIs.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Isomorphism</Slot>
      <Title>Why isomorphic metadata</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:modelxmlcontract:model-xml-contract" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:cliataglance:meta-cli-at-a-glance">
      <Body>`model.xml` declares the schema of a metadata workspace: which entities exist, which scalar properties they carry, and how they relate.

A model has one `&lt;Model name="..."&gt;` root and follows a small set of rules:

- `&lt;Entity name="Cube"&gt;` defines a record type; every entity has an implicit `Id`.
- `&lt;PropertyList&gt;` contains scalar fields. String is the default data type, properties are required by default, and `isRequired="false"` makes a property optional.
- `&lt;RelationshipList&gt;` contains references to other entities. Relationships are required by default.
- A relationship role is used when more than one relationship targets the same entity and the references need distinct meanings.
- XML instance containers and generated C# root collections use the deterministic `&lt;EntityName&gt;List` convention.

The model contract is intentionally small. Meaning that must survive generation belongs in entities, properties, and relationships rather than in parser conventions or surrounding prose.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>ModelXmlContract</Slot>
      <Title>Model XML contract</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:repositoryclis:repository-clis" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:summary:overview">
      <Body>The foundation is delivered through five command-line tools:

- **`meta`** authors and transforms model and instance workspaces, performs model-aware inspection and refactoring, imports external representations, and generates SQL and C# consumables.
- **`meta-cli`** models command grammars and supplies the shared parser, help, workspace-loading, and handler runtime used by the suite.
- **`meta-weave`** defines and validates sanctioned property bindings across models, then materializes those bindings when one combined workspace is needed.
- **`meta-docs`** combines generated reference facts with authored technical documentation, then merges and renders the public reference.
- **`meta-mesh`** declares the workspaces involved in a repository workflow and the ordered executable steps that operate on them.

BI-specific sanctioned models and command-line tools live in the separate `meta-bi` repository.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>RepositoryClis</Slot>
      <Title>Foundation command-line tools</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:summary:overview" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview">
      <Body>`meta` is a deterministic metadata backend for defining structured models once and carrying them across XML, SQL, and C# without semantic drift. XML workspaces provide a git-friendly authoring surface, while generated SQL and C# provide native relational and application surfaces over the same model and instance graph.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>Overview</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:versioncontrol:why-git-matters-for-metadata" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:isomorphism:why-isomorphic-metadata">
      <Body>A workspace is designed to behave well under version control:

- deterministic writer output keeps diffs stable and reviewable;
- model and instance changes can be reviewed with the same discipline as source code;
- branch and merge workflows can carry metadata evolution;
- refactors remain auditable through before-and-after workspace changes.

The XML writer uses stable ordering, UTF-8 without a byte-order mark, and LF line endings so representation noise does not obscure semantic changes.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>VersionControl</Slot>
      <Title>Why Git matters for metadata</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta:overview:narrative:workspacecontract:workspace-contract" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta:overview:narrative:versioncontrol:why-git-matters-for-metadata">
      <Body>A workspace is a directory with this baseline shape:

```text
workspace.xml
model.xml
instances/...
```

Instance data may be sharded across several files. Loading combines rows for the same entity; saving preserves the existing shard layout and writes new rows to that entity's primary shard.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>WorkspaceContract</Slot>
      <Title>Workspace contract</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:reference:narrative:summary:meta-meta-bi-reference" DocumentationSubjectId="public:reference">
      <Body>Command-line and model references for the current public MetaDocs suite.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>PlainText</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>Summary</Slot>
      <Title>meta + meta-bi reference</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:sqlsemantics:sql-as-modeled-structure" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:summary:overview">
      <Body>SQL is represented as structure rather than carried as an opaque script blob.

- **`MetaTransformScript`** imports the supported T-SQL surface into a typed syntax graph covering statement roots, query composition, joins, expressions, predicates, grouping, windowing, functions, and bounded mutation statements. The model emits semantically equivalent SQL and proves stability through `SQL -&gt; workspace -&gt; SQL -&gt; workspace` round trips.
- **`MetaTransformBinding`** resolves modeled source and target identifiers against explicit `MetaSchema` workspaces. It records rowsets, columns, source objects, target objects, and validation links, and checks target shape and data-type compatibility through sanctioned `MetaDataTypeConversion` policy.
- **`MetaSql`** carries deployable database structure, while `MetaSqlDeployManifest` makes source and live fingerprints, schema changes, destructive approvals, and deployment actions explicit before execution.

That shared understanding lets later layers reason from transform structure and binding evidence instead of reparsing SQL independently or guessing from text.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>SqlSemantics</Slot>
      <Title>SQL as modeled structure</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:modellayers:sanctioned-model-layers" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:sqlsemantics:sql-as-modeled-structure">
      <Body>The sanctioned models divide BI concerns at their natural ownership boundaries:

- **Source and type contracts:** `MetaSchema` captures systems, schemas, tables, fields, keys, and relationships from SQL Server. `MetaDataType` and `MetaDataTypeConversion` carry semantic types and explicit mappings into runtime type systems.
- **Data architecture:** `MetaRawDataVault` and `MetaBusinessDataVault` model raw and governed vault structures. `MetaDataWarehouse` models dimensions, facts, grain, business keys, roles, snapshots, bridges, and slowly changing dimensions. Separate implementation workspaces own physical SQL naming, keys, platform columns, defaults, and indexes.
- **Transform and database realization:** `MetaTransformScript`, `MetaTransformBinding`, `MetaSql`, and `MetaSqlDeployManifest` carry understood SQL, schema contracts, deployable objects, and controlled deployment.
- **Analytical semantics:** `MetaAnalytics` defines portable tables, attributes, hierarchies, measures, aggregation behavior, relationships, perspectives, roles, cultures, and translations before an engine is selected.
- **Analytical targets:** `MetaTabular` owns DAX measures, calculation groups, partitions, KPIs, and tabular security. `MetaMultiDimensional` owns cubes, measure groups, MDX, named sets, actions, partitions, and multidimensional security.
- **Execution and assurance:** `MetaDataQuality`, `MetaPipeline`, and `MetaOrchestration` turn modeled transform and access evidence into reviewable checks, executable task chains, dependency graphs, synchronization policy, and runtime evidence.

`meta-convert` performs explicit conversions between sanctioned model surfaces, keeping portable intent separate from target-specific implementation details.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>ModelLayers</Slot>
      <Title>Sanctioned model layers</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:operationalevidence:model-driven-execution-and-evidence" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:modellayers:sanctioned-model-layers">
      <Body>The runtime tools consume modeled evidence produced by the layers before them:

- **`meta-data-quality`** traverses the typed transform graph to discover reviewable integrity, optionality, fanout, duplicate, join-pattern, and filter-consensus candidates. Binding evidence can restrict generation to transforms whose source and target contracts are already proven.
- **`meta-pipeline`** executes modeled transform-backed and external-process tasks, records the exact transform and binding used, and preserves row, batch, timeout, fingerprint, audit, and failure evidence.
- **`meta-orchestration`** derives the provable dependency graph from pipeline tasks and bound object reads and writes. Explicit ordering, lock compatibility, synchronization, and failure branches remain modeled policy instead of being buried in scheduler behavior.
- **Target CLIs** realize modeled SQL, Tabular, and MultiDimensional workspaces through deployment and processing commands owned by the target model.

Automation therefore follows from explicit contracts. When additional knowledge is required, it enters as modeled policy that engineers and agents can inspect alongside the inferred evidence.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>OperationalEvidence</Slot>
      <Title>Model-driven execution and evidence</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
    <DocumentationNarrative Id="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:endtoend:from-source-contracts-to-analytical-targets" DocumentationSubjectId="public:meta-bi:overview" PreviousNarrativeId="public:meta-bi:overview:narrative:operationalevidence:model-driven-execution-and-evidence">
      <Body>A typical path can begin with a live system extracted into `MetaSchema`, then move through explicit data-type policy, vault or dimensional architecture, modeled and bound SQL transforms, generated database assets, data-quality review, pipeline execution, orchestration, and a portable `MetaAnalytics` model projected into Tabular or MultiDimensional form.

Teams compose the sanctioned workspaces that match their architecture. At every handoff, the input and output remain inspectable model instances instead of disappearing into generator configuration or unstructured deployment scripts.</Body>
      <BodyFormat>Markdown</BodyFormat>
      <Origin>Authored</Origin>
      <ReviewStatus>Current</ReviewStatus>
      <Slot>EndToEnd</Slot>
      <Title>From source contracts to analytical targets</Title>
    </DocumentationNarrative>
  </DocumentationNarrativeList>
</MetaDocs>
